Guide to the University Archives Directories, Guides Handbooks Collection
SJSU Library Special Collections Archives
San José State University Archives Directories, Guides Handbooks Collection
1920-1997
1941-1976
MSS-2010-05-04
San José State University
17 boxes (6.88 linear feet)
San José State University Library. San José, California 95192-0028
The San José State University Archives Directories, Guides Handbooks, 1920-1997 (bulk 1941-1976) consists of handbooks and directories targeted to students, faculty and staff. The directories contain address and telephone lists of students, staff, and faculty. The handbooks, mostly produced for student usage, give a comprehensive view of University procedures, resources, and traditions. The records consist of printed materials, bound and unbound guides and handbooks, directories, and pamphlets. This collection is arranged into four series: Series I. Directories, 1921-1997 (bulk 1945-1981); Series II. Student Handbooks, 1923-1997 (bulk 1941-1967): Series III; Staff Reference Guides, 1962-1997 (bulk 1961-1978); Series IV. Miscellaneous, 1902-1979 (bulk 1934-1969).
Access
The collection is open for research.
Project Information
This finding aid was created as part of the Survey and Cataloging Project, a two-year San José State University Library grant project funded by the National Historical Publications and Records Commission. The project began in 2008. The Project Director is Danelle Moon. The Project Archivist is Erin Louthen.
Organizational History
In 1857 the San Francisco Board of Education established Minns' Evening Normal School for current and prospective teachers in the city. Named after its principal, George W. Minns, the institution was formally established as the first California State Normal School by the State Legislature in 1862. A decade later, the Legislature voted to move the Normal School to San José, and the school relocated to its new home on Washington Square prior to the fall term of 1872. After a fire destroyed the Normal School building in 1880, the Legislature authorized $200,000 to construct a new building on the same site. Completed in 1881, the building was commonly referred to as the Second State Normal School. After several names and curriculum changes, Minns' Normal School is now San José State University, offering more than 134 bachelor's and master's degrees with 110 concentrations, and is recognized as one of the top public universities granting such degrees in the West.
Bibliography
Gilbert, Benjamin F., and Burdick, Charles. Washington Square, 1857-1979: The History of San José State University. San José, California: San José State University, 1980.
San José State University. About SJSU. http://www.sjsu.edu/about_sjsu/
Walsh, James P. San José State University: An Interpretive History, 1950-2000. San José, California: San José State University, 2003.
Related Material
San José State University Faculty Wives Club Records, MSS-2010-03-02. San José State University Library Special Collections Archives.
Scope and Content of Collection
The San José State University Archives Directories, Guides Handbooks, 1920-1997 (bulk 1941-1976) consists of handbooks and directories targeted to students, faculty, and staff. The directories contain address and telephone lists of students, staff and faculty. The handbooks, mostly produced for student usage, give a comprehensive view of University procedures, resources, and traditions. The records consist of printed materials, bound and unbound guides and handbooks, directories, and pamphlets.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into four series: Series I. Directories, 1921-1997 (bulk 1945-1981): Series II. Student Handbooks, 1923-1997 (bulk 1941-1967): Series III. Staff Reference Guides, 1962-1997 (bulk 1961-1978); Series IV. Miscellaneous, 1902-1979 (bulk 1934-1969).
Subject Headings
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
San Jose State Teachers College -- History.; San Jose State College -- History.; San José State University -- History.; San Jose State Teachers College -- Directories.; San Jose State College -- Directories.; Education, Higher -- California -- San José.; Universities and College -- California -- San José.
Collection Contents
- Directories, 1921-1961; Series I:; 6 boxes
  Series Scope and Content Summary
  The materials in this series include student telephone directories, the Blue Key also known as the Spartan Key, and faculty staff directories of varying size and formats.
  Arrangement
  Files are arranged alphabetically by format, and then chronologically within each folder.
  - Student and Faculty Directories, Faculty Directory, 1921-1961 (Box 1)
  - Student and Faculty Directories, Departmental Telephone Directory, 1925-1961 (Box 2)
  - Faculty Directories, alphabetical edition Office and Department edition, New Faculty addendums, Report on shifts in Faculty and Staff, Student and Faculty Directories, 1960-1966 (Box 3)
  - University Telephone Directories, Student Directories, 1966-1981 (Box 4)
  - University Telephone Directories, 1982-1993 (Box 5)
  - Fifty Year Reunion Directories, 1979-1986 (Box 6)
- Student Handbooks, 1923-1997; Series II:
  This series consists of handbooks that were distributed to the student body. Early examples include the Campus Compass and A Spartan from the Start. The handbooks describe school regulations, dress codes and provides come context for campus traditions, as well as maps documenting the locations of specific student spots. Also included in this series are pamphlets produced for current and prospective students on financial aid, student activities, and night school.
  - Student Handbooks, 1953-1967 (Box 7)
  - Pamphlets, 1949-1963 (Box 8)
  - Activities Calendars, Pamphlets, Student Hanbooks, 1942-1979 (Box 9)
  - Student Handbooks, 1923-1953 (Box 10)
  - Student Handbooks, Pamphlets, Student Newspapers, 1966-1996 (Box 11)
- Staff Reference Guides, 1962-1997; Series III:
  This series consists of reference guides produced for SJSU staff and faculty. The guides provide information on human resources, contact information for departments, emergency safety information, as well as policies and procedures.
  - Staff Reference Books, Pamphlet Addendums, 1961-1974 (Box 12)
  - Staff Reference Books, 1971-1977 (Box 13)
  - Staff Reference Books, Pamphlet, 1985-1997 (Box 14)
  - Emergency Handbooks, 1989 (Box 15)
- Miscellaneous, 1920-1979; Series IV:
  This series consists of miscellaneous directories, handbooks, programs, pamphlets and printed matter.
  - Faculty and Student Directories, Student Directories, Student Handbooks, Staff Reference Books, Programs, Printed Materials, 1921-1969 (Box 16)
  - Staff Handbooks, Student Handbooks, Printed Materials, Associated Student Body Constitutions, 1920-1997 (Box 17)